Yaojie Liu

CONTACT Information Department of Computer Science and Engineering, E-mail: liuyaoj1@msu.edu Michigan State University, Phone: (614)-886-6885

East Lansing, MI 48824, USA Web: www.cse.msu.edu/~liuyaoj1/

RESEARCH INTERESTS Computer Vision, Deep Learning, Face Analysis, Synthesis, Biometrics, Low-level Vision, Audio-Visual Modeling, Image Forensic.

EDUCATION

Michigan State University, MI, USA

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science, May 2016 - May. 2021 (Expected)

- Dissertation Title: "Face Anti-Spoofing: Detection, Generalization, and Visualization"
- Advisor: Dr. Xiaoming Liu
- Thesis committee: Xiaoming Liu (chair), Anil Jain, Arun Ross, Daniel Morris
- GPA: 3.67/4

The Ohio State University, OH, USA

M.S. in Computer Science, Sept. 2014 - Apr. 2016

- Research Title: "Global and Local Fitting of Facial Landmarks and Action Units (AUs)"
- Advisor: Dr. Aleix Martinez
- GPA: 3.88/4

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China, Sichuan, China

B.E. in Communication Engineering, Sept. 2010 - Apr. 2014

- Dissertation Title: "Image Inpainting"
- Advisor: Dr. Chang Shu
- GPA: 3.92/4

RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS

In the area of face anti-spoofing, I lead the R&D at our team, publish 7 papers, 1 under review, release 2 databases, file 1 patent, organize 2 half-day tutorials and 1 full-day demo. The papers receive overall >400 citations, the databases are distributed to >600 research groups, and our code receive ~ 300 stars & 86 forks on GitHub. In U.S. government-organized independent evaluation, our face anti-spoofing solution can achieve 98.4% TDR at 0.2% FDR and 1.0 AUC. Our research of face anti-spoofing is covered by MSUToday [News]. Here are some examples of our face anti-spoofing systems [Video].

Publications

I have >500 citations according to **Google Scholar**, and my h-index is 6. (* denotes equal contribution)

Conference Papers:

- 1. Y. Liu, X. Huang, R. Liu, X. Liu, "Facial Foreign Shadow Detection and Removal via Spatio-Temporal Consistency," under review at IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR' 21), 2021.
- 2. X. Liu, Y. Liu, J. Chen, X. Liu, "PSSC-Net: Progressive Spatio-Channel Correlation Network for Image Manipulation Detection and Localization," under review at IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR'21), 2021.
- 3. Y. Liu, J. Stehouwer, X. Liu, "On Disentangling Spoof Traces for Generic Face Anti-Spoofing," Proc. European Conference of Commputer Vision (ECCV'20), 2020. (26% Acceptance Rate)

[PDF] [Code] [Short Video] [Long Video]

- J. Stehouwer, A. Jourabloo, Y. Liu, X. Liu, "Noise Modeling, Synthesis and Classification for Generic Object Anti-Spoofing," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR'20), 2020. (25% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Code] [Database] [Short Video]
- Y. Liu, J. Stehouwer, A. Jourabloo, X. Liu, "Deep Tree Learning for Zero-shot Face Anti-spoofing," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR'19), 2019. (Oral, Best Paper Finalist, 5.6% Acceptance Rate.) [PDF] [Code] [Database] [Poster]
- Y. Liu*, A. Jourabloo*, X. Liu, "Face De-Spoofing: Anti-Spoofing via Noise Modeling," Proc. European Conference of Commputer Vision (ECCV'18), 2018. (31.8% Acceptance Rate) [PDF]
 [Code] [Poster]
- 7. Y. Liu*, A. Jourabloo*, X. Liu, "Learning Deep Models for Face Anti-Spoofing: Binary or Auxiliary Supervision," IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR'18), 2018. (30% Acceptance Rate) [PDF] [Database] [Poster]
- 8. Y. Liu, A. Jourabloo, W. Ren, X. Liu, "Dense Face Alignment," International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCVW'17) Workshop on Analysis and Modeling of Faces and Gestures (AMFG), 2017. [PDF] [Code] [Poster]
- 9. Y. Liu*, Y. Atoum*, A. Jourabloo*, X. Liu, "Face Anti-Spoofing Using Patch and Depth-Based CNNs," International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB'17), 2017. [PDF] [Poster]
- R. Zhao, Y. Wang, C.F. Benitez-Quiroz, Y. Liu, A.M. Martinez, "Fast and Precise Face Alignment and 3D Shape Reconstruction from a Single 2D Image." European Conference on Computer Vision Workshop (ECCVW'16), 2016. [PDF]
- 11. Y. Liu, C. Shu, "A Comparison of Image Inpainting Techniques." International Conference on Graphic and Image Processing (ICGIP), 2015. [Link]

Journal Papers:

- 12. Y. Liu, X. Liu, "Physics-Guided Spoof Trace Disentanglement for Generic Face Anti-Spoofing" under review in IEEE Transaction on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI), 2020.
- C. Shu, Y. Liu, "Inpainting: Survey and Experiments" International Journal of Signal Processing, Image Processing and Pattern Recognition, Vol. 9, Issue. 10, pp. 21-36, October 2016.
 [Link]
- 14. Y. Liu, C. Shu, "Dynamic Gesture Localization and Recognition Algorithm Based on Skeletonization" Electronic Science and Technology, Vol. 3, pp. 005, 2014. (in Chinese) [Link]

Book Chapters:

15. Y. Liu, J. Stehouwer, A. Jourabloo, X. Liu, "Presentation Attack Detection for Face in Mobile Phones" Selfie Biometrics, Ajita Rattani, Reza Derakhahani, and Arun Ross, Eds, Springer-Verlag, 2019. [PDF]

Working EXPERIENCES

Computer Vision Intern

Bosch Research, Sunnyvale, CA

May 2020 - Aug. 2020

AI Research Intern

Research topic: Audio-visual Modeling

Apple Inc., Cupertino, CA

May 2019 - Aug. 2019

Research Assistant

May 2016 - Now

Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI

Professional SERVICES

Co-Organizer/Lecturer

- Half-day Tutorial: "Secure the Face System: Recent Advances on Detecting Face Spoof Attacks and Digital Face Manipulation", International Joint Conference on Biometrics (IJCB), 2020
- Half-day Tutorial: "Face Anti-Spoofing: Past, Present and Future", International Conference on Biometrics: Theory Applications and Systems (BTAS), 2019

Conference Reviewer

CVPR'19-21, ICCV'19, ECCV'20, NeurIPS'20, AAAI'20-21, WACV'21, ACCV'20, BTAS'18, ICB'19, ICME'20, PRCV'19-20

Journal Reviewer

TPAMI, TIP, TIFS, CVIU, Neurocomputing, TOMM, JCST, JEI, Image and Vision Computing, IET Computer Vision, IEEE Access, TBIOM

Research Mentorship

William Ren (High School Student, 2016)

Xiaohan Zhang (B.S. in C.S., 2017, Michigan State University)

Xiaohong Liu (Ph.D. in C.S., 2020, McMaster University)

Talks

• Face Anti-Spoofing: Detect, Visualize, and Generalize Invited talk, Sichuan University, China.

Jan. 2020

Jan. 2020

• Face Anti-Spoofing: Detect, Visualize, and Generalize Invited talk, UESTC, China.

Sept. 2019

• Deep Tree Net for Face Anti-spoofing MSU/ND vision workshop, Notre Dame IN.

Jun. 2019

• Deep Tree Net for Face Anti-spoofing Oral Presentation, CVPR.

Apr. 2017

• Dense Face Alignment Midwest vision workshop, Chicago IL.

Honors and Awards	ECCV 2020 Outstanding Reviewer (215 selected out of 2830 reviewers by Area Chairs),	2020
	Awarded College of Engineering Dissertation Completion Fellowship, MSU	2020
	CVPR 2019 Best Paper Finalist (45 papers selected out of 1294 total accepted papers)	2020
	Honorable Mention, Engineering Graduate Research Symposium, MSU	2018
	Awarded College of Engineering Distinguished Fellowship, MSU	2016
	Best Bachelor Thesis Award, UESTC	2014
	First Rank, People's Scholarship for Excellent University Student, China	2013
	Second Rank, People's Scholarship for Excellent University Student, China	2012
	Granted research fund from Institute of Electronic Science and Technology, UESTC	
	Granted research fund from Undergraduate Innovation Foundation, UESTC	
	First Rank, People´s Scholarship for Excellent University Student, China	2011
PATENTS	Y. Liu, A. Jourabloo, X. Liu, "Improved Spoof Detection for Facial Recognition," U.S. Ser	rial No.

62/626,486, filed on Feb 05, 2018.

Demos

"Real-time Face Anti-spoofing System" at CVPR'18. [Link]

Jun. 2018

SKILLS

- Programming Language: Python, C/C++, Java, Git, Bash, HTML, SQL, R, LATEX, Lisp
- Operating Systems: Linux, MacOS, Windows
- Signal Processing: Matlab
- Computer Vision Library: OpenCV
- Deep Learning: Tensorflow, PyTorch, MatConvNet, Caffe.